Guide to the ECOS Records, 1969 - 2001
University Archives Duke University
ECOS records 1969 - 2001
Duke ECOS.
1.5 Linear Feet 1,000 Items
University Archives, Duke University
ECOS (Environmentally Conscious Organization of Students) is a Duke University and Durham, N.C. environmental activist group founded in 1969. ECOS is also known as the Environmental Alliance. The records of ECOS include articles of incorporation, event reports, member lists, ECOS constitutions, bylaws, minutes, correspondence, printed e-mail correspondence, a webpage printout, financial materials, clippings, flyers, meeting announcements, and newsletters. Major subjects include Duke University students, ECOS, Duke Environmental Center, Durham (N.C.) history, New Hope Dam, Eno River State Park, environmental protection, public interest groups, political activity, and student groups. Materials range in date from 1969 to 1990 (bulk 1970-1973).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The ECOS Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975 and 1980.
Historical Note
ECOS (Environmentally Conscious Organization of Students) was formed at Duke University in 1969. ECOS grew to include members of the Durham, N.C. community in their efforts to educate people on environmental concerns. Other environmental groups active around the Raleigh-Durham, N.C. area in the early 1970s were: Chapel Hill ECOS, Organization for Environmental Quality (Raleigh), and the Conservation Council of North Carolina.
ECOS members were advocates of University-wide recycling, conservative population growth, and responsible consumption. At Duke University, members proposed an environmental studies program and organized a teach-in. ECOS came to be known for their recycling efforts, employing a small staff to collect newspapers, aluminum, and glass for resale to local companies.
Some of ECOS' awareness-raising activities included a Bike-a-Thon between Raleigh and Durham, protesting the development of the Eno River area, protesting construction of the New Hope Dam, and lobbying for environmentally sound work spaces. The Eno River Park project was particularly important to the Durham, N.C. region. In the early 1970s, ECOS and supporters led a campaign to save the Eno River area from commercial development. Due to ECOS' protest efforts, the city of Durham withdrew its efforts to construct a reservoir. The Eno River State Park was established in 1972.
As of 2003, ECOS is known as the Environmental Alliance and is active at Duke University.
Collection Overview
The ECOS records include correspondence, establishment and governance documents, meeting minutes, events information, financial materials, a statement of purpose, and materials relating to ECOS projects and causes. The most significant ECOS projects within these records include the Eno River Park project, the New Hope Dam project, and Carolina Power and Light Company's proposed power plant in Wake County. The records also include publicity, clippings, and other printed material related to ECOS, the Duke Environmental Center, and the Environmental Coordinating Council at Duke.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
ECOS (Durham, N.C.)
Environmental protection -- North Carolina
Eno River State Park (N.C.)
Duke ECOS
Duke University. Environmental Alliance
Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.
Duke University -- Students -- Political activity
Duke University -- Students
Durham (N.C.) -- History
New Hope Dam (N.C.)
Public interest -- Societies, etc.
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bike-a-Thon events, 1972-1976 (Folder 2)
  - Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971-1972 (Folder 3)
  - Chapter establishment and tax status, 1970, undated (Folder 4)
  - ECOS constitution and bylaws, undated (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Folder 6)
  - Duke Environmental Center, 1973 (Folder 7)
  - Eno River Park project, 1970-1971 (Folder 8)
  - Environmental Coordinating Council, 1970-1971 (Folder 9)
  - Environmental studies proposal, ca. 1970 (Folder 10)
  - Environmental teach-in, ca. 1970 (Folder 11)
  - Financial materials, ca. 1970 (Folder 12)
  - Pamphlets and artwork, undated (Folder 13)
  - New Hope Dam project, 1970-1971 (Folder 14)
  - Operations and Funding Committee correspondence, 1970-1972 (Folder 15)
  - General publicity, undated (Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1970-1979 (Folder 17)
  - ECOS statement of purpose, undated (Folder 18)
  - The Duke Green Guide, 1990 (Folder 19)
  - ECOS newsletter, ca. 1970, 1973, 1974 (Folder 20)
  - Position paper, Carolina Power and Light Company's Proposed Power Plant in Wake County, 1973 (Folder 21)
  - Printed webpage, 2001 (Folder 22)
  - Printed e-mail correspondence, 2001 (Folder 23)
Related Material
NCPIRG records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Office of the Chancellor. Environmental Concerns Committee records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Environmental Center [Small Collections].
University Archives, Duke University.